Guide to the Records of the National Jewish Welfare Board, undated, 1889-1995 (bulk 1917-1990) *I-337
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
- Subgroup IV: Affiliated Organizations, undated, 1889-1979 (bulk 1930-1975); 75 linear feet.
  - Series C: World Federation of YM & YWHAs and JCCs, 1927-1975 (bulk 1940-1970); 46.5 linear feet.
    1. Interchange of ideas and experiences and the provision of opportunities for effective cooperation between the national organizations.
    2. The utilization of the machinery of the organization to foster the Jewish Center Movement in all countries where feasible and desirable.
    3. Undertaking such other functions as may, from time to time, appear to the Federation likely to benefit its affiliated national member bodies.48
    The World Fed was JWB's link to the JCCs and YMHAs around the world. The series contains the correspondence and reports exchanged by the affiliated organizations and JWB. It was also a critical player in the building and funding of the Jerusalem Y's new campus in 1967.
    The Geographic Files document JWB's relationship with YMHAs, JCCS, and Jewish Youth Groups around the world and is similar to the Countries Overseas and Foreign Countries files. The documents of the Jerusalem Y follow its opening in 1950 to the dedication of the new building in 1967. Included are the blueprints of the new building, records of payments from fund raising efforts, and photographs of the plaques placed throughout the facility to recognize those who gave substantial amounts of money. The Meetings and Biennial material highlights the World Fed's part in JWB's Biennial Conventions and their own executive committee meetings. Asher Tarmon's files consist of reports and correspondence that mostly predate his directorship of World Fed and documents his role in Jewish educational programming and the building of the Jerusalem Y's new facility.
    Of special interest are the materials relating to Louis Kraft, the dedication given by President Shazar at the opening of the new Jerusalem Y, addresses given by Ambassador Avraham Harman and his wife Zena in 1962 and 1963 on why the new Jerusalem Y building was needed, proposals by the government of Israel for the utilization of the funds accumulated under the informational media guaranty program, Association for Jewish Youth of England, and a 68 page report by Morris Levin on the Jerusalem Y found in the Countries Overseas files.
    Types of material include correspondence, bulletins, reports, "Y's of the World", contribution information, biographical information, interview transcripts, contracts, maps (located in Oversized Materials Subgroup), a plaque, resumes, program materials, newspaper clippings, press releases, meeting minutes and agendas, memoranda, building plans (some are located in Oversized Subgroup), photographs (located in Audio/Visual Materials Subgroup), proceedings, prize ribbons, sound recordings (located in Audio/Visual Materials Subgroup), and a canvas apron from the Jerusalem Y.
    48 Articles of Federation of "The World Federation of YMHA's and Jewish Community Centers." 1961, I-337 NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
    Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governance/Series C: Central Records Center/Subseries 3: History Files; Subgroup I: Governance/Series D: Conventions and Committees/Subseries 1: Biennials; Subgroup II: JCC/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 3: Field Reports.
    Restrictions: Several folders are restricted due to the fragility of their contents
    Note: Miscellaneous box 16 is located at end of entire collection. The material relates to the Asher Tarmon Files.
  - Series D: YMHA, 1889-1968 (bulk 1930-1965); 21 linear feet.
    This series is divided into the following subseries: Annual Meetings (1938-1944), Geographic Files (1935-1968) and YMHA Movement (1889-1944). Arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by state.
    The series highlights the planning and construction of new YMHAs and JCCs throughout the country and Canada and documents the growth of the JCC and YMHA movement throughout the country and Canada.
    Of special interest is the story of the Grossman's family from Massachusetts who started the DIY home center with Grossman's (1956 Quincy, MA), The Associate a pamphlet from 1889-1890 devoted to the interests of the Philadelphia YMHA, and the bound minutes of the Pennsylvania Federation of YM & YWHA 1910-1940.
    Types of material include annual meeting proceedings, correspondence, memoranda, newspaper clippings, building plans (located in Oversized Materials Subgroup) and reports.
    Related Materials: Subgroup II: JCC/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 3: Field Reports and Subseries 6: Regional Area Files.
    Restrictions: one folder is restricted due to the fragility of the contents.
- Subgroup V: Audio-Visual Materials, undated, 1913-1986 (bulk 1918-1982); 28.5 linear feet (plus film cans and rolled photographs)
  Governance; Jewish Community Centers; Veterans' Affairs; Affiliated Organizations. See Photo Archivist for access to photographic materials. Audio-visual materials not yet available for research.
  This subgroup consists of photographs and other audio-visual materials removed from the earlier subgroups. In most cases, photographs were replaced with either photocopied images or separation sheets. However, in the processing of the Commission on Jewish Chaplaincy (CJC) files, in the Veterans' Affairs Subgroup a slightly different procedure was followed. (See note.) All photographs are notated to indicate their original locations; thus the researcher may examine any documents related to the image.
  A wide variety of activities are captured here, ranging from conferences to religious services, from photographs of soldiers to photographs of swim meets. Photographs of the exteriors of JCCs, YM-YWHAs, and military bases from throughout the world can be found here, as can photographs of activities both in the United States and abroad. The wide range of activities which JCCs provided for members of all ages is well represented, as is JWB's involvement with prominent members of the public. Individuals pictured here include political figures such as Richard Nixon, Dwight David Eisenhower, John F. Kennedy, Harry Truman, Eleanor Roosevelt and athletes such as the Harlem Globetrotters and Sid Gordon of the New York Giants. JWB's actions during the first and second world wars are strongly represented here by photographs of chaplains engaged in a wide range of activities, and by photographs of soldiers and veterans. Of particular note are some images of chaplains and soldiers with Concentration Camp survivors.
  In addition to photographs, a variety of other audio-visual formats can be found here. These include VHS and BETA videotapes submitted by JCCs as contestants for JWB's Communications Awards, slides, negatives, filmstrips, and film reels.
  Note on processing of CJC photographs: Photographs in the chaplains' and lay leaders' files were copied only when they were directly linked to documentation. However, in all cases when photographs were removed, a form was placed in the original folder, indicating that photographs have been removed and can be found at the end of the collection.
- Subgroup VI: Oversized Materials, undated, 1922-1985; 5 linear feet and 3 OS1 boxes.
  Governance (undated, 1939, 1951, 1958); Jewish Community Centers (undated, 1922-1957, 1961, 1963-1975, 1985); Veterans' Affairs (undated); Affiliated Organizations: World Federation of YM-YWHA and JCCs (undated, 1950) Miscellaneous (1950) (Arrangement mirrors layout of the first four subgroups.)
  This subgroup consists of oversized materials removed from the other series. Materials of note include architectural plans and drawings for JCCs and YM-YWHAs throughout the U.S.A. and overseas. (These include plans for the Jerusalem Y.) Also located here are posters promoting events sponsored by the Lecture Bureau, several newspapers reporting on the 1972 flood of the Susquehanna River, and bound volumes of the JWB Circle. Other materials include maps, charts, blueprints, spreadsheets, certificates, and census tracts.
  Related Materials: see Arrangement.